<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>T1D | Bio-Rants</title>
    <link>/tags/t1d/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/t1d/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>T1D</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>T1D</title>
      <link>/tags/t1d/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>β cells cis-regulatory networks and type 1 diabetes</title>
      <link>/project/betacells-t1d/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/betacells-t1d/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Type 1 diabetes (T1D) is a multifactorial disease that develops as a result of the interaction of genetic predisposition, environment and immune (dis)regulation. When this factors converge, the disease is triggered, with a pancreatic islets immune infiltration (insulitis) that results in a selective destruction of pancreatic beta-cells, the sole source of insulin in the body. Once the clinical symptoms manifest, beta-cell mass is almost depleted and the patients become insulin-dependent for life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, studies have been focusing in understanding the causes of the immune dis-regulation and developing treatments that prevent the recognition of auto-antigens. Nevertheless, the exact molecular mechanisms that underly how the disease is triggered and the nature of the immune dis-regulation is still unclear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the focus has been directed towards the immune system, beta-cells have been con- sidered passive bystanders of the process. However, it is now clear that during insulitis and before their destruction begins, a dialog is established between beta-cells and immune cells mediated by the secretion of cytokines and chemokines. Recently, it has been postulated that a misunderstanding in this dialog is what leads to beta-cell destruction, thus assigning to beta-cells a central and active role in the disease progression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In support of this hypothesis, many T1D associated genes were found to be expressed in beta-cells. Moreover, GWAS studies which identify SNPs associated with risk of developing T1D, with the important exception of the HLA loci, failed in identifying causal variants with a functional impact in immune cells. Interestingly, many of these SNPs are not found in coding regions of the genome, pointing to a possible regulatory role of these variants that could be exert by affecting non-coding regulatory elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hypothesis that drives this project is that beta-cells regulatory networks involved in response to T1D-like stimuli are responsible for a fraction of the genetic signal associated with T1D. Accordingly, our main goal consists on characterizing tissue-specific cis-regulatory networks critical to the activation and modulation of beta-cell survival.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
